George Willis Johnson Papers
George Willis Johnson Papers
1916-1956
Johnson, George Willis, 1880-1953.
24 linear ft.
Papers of the American business executive. President of Endicott-Johnson Corporation, 1930-1949. Correspondence, incoming and outgoing (1916-1954); corporate mimeographed and printed notices to employees (1925-1949); clippings (1931-1947); photographs, articles, and speeches relating to the shoe manufacturer.
149089
Biographical History
George Willis Johnson (1880-1953) was an American businessman. Born in Plymouth, Massachusetts to George F. and Lucie (Willis) Johnson, he grew up in Johnson City, New York, where he attended public schools. He also attended Worcester Academy and Dean Academy in Massachusettes. In 1900 he married Lula Seagers, and they had three children; Marion Young, Frank A. and Wilma M. Smith. George Johnson was active in community affairs, and an enthusiastic athlete, interested in baseball, golf, bowling, hunting, and fishing.
At the age of 18 George Johnson started working as a packer in the Endicott-Johnson Company, and later on he worked most of his life in the tanneries doing various jobs. In 1919 when Endicott-Johnson was incorporated, he was elected to the Board of Directors. He served as president of the corporation from 1930 to 1949.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George W. Johnson Papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, and clippings, arranged in eight series.
Correspondence includes both incoming and outgoing, followed by correspondence of others. Subject files consists of published material and correspondence, and includes correspondence with both individuals and businesses as well as legal documents, press copy, reports, and various employee benefit information (wages, homes, pensions, etc).
Manuscripts consists of speeches, statements, and poems of George W. Johnson, George F. Johnson, and others.
Mimeographed and printed notices includes communications from the Johnsons or other members of the corporation to workers and other personnel.
Photographs include as subjects Endicott-Johnson officers, workers, and plant, as well as George F. Johnson and other individuals
Workers pages consists of clippings of pages from the Binghamton Sun. This page was published daily and contained news about and of special interest to Endicott-Johnson workers.
Published material includes articles, brochures, bulletin-board notices, magazines, newsletters and newspaper clippings.
Arrangement of the Collection
Incoming correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author; outgoing is arranged chronologically. Subject files and Photographs are arranged alphabetically by subject. Mimeographed and printed notices are arranged chronologically. Published material is arranged alphabetically by type; bulletin-board notices are arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Business and Industry; New York State; Johnson, George Willis, 1880-1953 -- Archives.; Endicott-Johnson Corporation -- Employees.; Endicott-Johnson Corporation -- History -- Sources.; Executives -- New York (State); Footwear industry -- New York (State); Industrial relations -- United States.; Shoe industry -- Employees.; Shoe industry -- New York (State); Manufactures -- United States.; Endicott (N.Y.) -- Industries.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Speeches (documents); Executives.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Incoming
    - A, 1941; 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - American Cancer Society, 1951; 1952 (Box 1)
    - B, 1932; 1937,; 1941-1948,; 1950-1953 (Box 1)
    - Berk, Ben, 1939 (Box 1)
    - C, 1940-1942; 1949-1953 (Box 1)
    - Canadian International Paper Co., 1951; 1952 (Box 1)
    - Chestnut Canoe Co., 1952 (Box 1)
    - Clark, Ralph B., 1950-1953 (Box 1)
    - Clay, Ryburn, 1934; 1938-1940,; 1945-1947,; 1951 (Box 1)
    - Clay, Zaida Willis, 1940; 1941,; 1945,; undated (Box 1)
    - Cordiner, Ralph J., 1951 (Box 1)
    - D, 1921; 1937,; 1945,; 1951-1953 (Box 1)
    - Durham, J. Edward Jr., 1951; undated (Box 1)
    - E, 1937; 1938,; 1942,; 1948,; 1950-1953 (Box 1)
    - Endicott Leather Works Union, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
    - F, G, 1916; 1937,; 1938,; 1941,; 1944-1946,; 1948,; 1950-1953 (Box 1)
    - Georgia-Hanks Co., 1947; 1948,; 1951 (Box 2)
    - Goldman, Sacks and Co., 1945; 1946,; 1950,; 1952 (Box 2)
    - Gurley, Mirabel, 1948; 1949,; 1952,; undated (Box 2)
    - H, I, 1941; 1944-1946,; 1948,; 1950-1953 (Box 2)
    - Head, Clarence C., 1951 (Box 2)
    - Hill, William, 1951; 1952 (Box 2)
    - Hinman, Howard and Kattel, 1951; 1952 (Box 2)
    - J, K, 1937; 1942-1946,; 1948-1953 (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Charles Jr., 1941; 1942-1944,; 1946,; 1949-1953,; undated (Box 2)
    - Johnson, George F., 1916; 1930,; 1935-1939,; 1945,; 1946 (Box 2)
    - Johnson, Lula, 1938; 1940,; 1942,; 1943,; 1950,; 1951,; undated (Box 2)
    - L, 1951-1953 (Box 2)
    - Laurentian Air Services, limited, 1951 (Box 2)
    - A.C. Lawrence Leather Co., 1944; 1951,; 1952 (Box 2)
    - Lehigh Portland Cement Co., 1938; 1941,; 1945,; 1948 (Box 2)
    - Leonhard, John, 1950-1953 (Box 2)
    - Leonhard, Russell, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
    - M, 1937; 1944,; 1948,; 1949,; 1951-1953 (Box 3)
    - MacLean, Charles Stuart, 1951; 1952 (Box 3)
    - Merlean, J.O., 1951 (Box 3)
    - Mills, Leo E., 1938; 1946,; 1949,; 1952 (Box 3)
    - Morrissette, Wilbrod Mr. and Mrs., 1951; 1952 (Box 3)
    - N, O, P, 1937; 1941,; 1944,; 1946,; 1947,; 1950-1953 (Box 3)
    - National War Labor Board, 1943-1945 (Box 3)
    - O'Neil, Ruth, 1949; 1950-1952,; undated (Box 3)
    - Poirier, J.H. and Sons, 1949-1952 (Box 3)
    - Quebec Department of Fish and Game, 1944; 1947,; 1951,; 1952 (Box 3)
    - Quebec Federation of Fish and Game Association, 1951; 1952 (Box 3)
    - R, 1938; 1943,; 1945,; 1948-1952 (Box 3)
    - Regan, Bertha, 1946; 1949,; 1951; secretary to George F. (Box 3)
    - Robertson, George, 1949; nephew (Box 3)
    - Robertson, Zada, 1939-1941; 1945,; undated; sister (Box 3)
    - Robertson, William, 1945; 1946 (Box 3)
    - Ronnsefell, Dr. Clifford G., 1945 (Box 3)
    - S, 1939; 1942,; 1944,; 1946-1953 (Box 3)
    - Stanford, Linda, 1945; 1951-1953 (Box 3)
    - Swartwood, Howard A., 1938; 1939,; 1941-1946,; 1948,; 1951-1953,; undated (Box 4)
    - T, U, W, Y, 1936-1938; 1941-1945,; 1948,; 1949,; 1951-1953 (Box 4)
    - Taber-Wheeler Co. Inc., 1933; 1938 (Box 4)
    - Tei, Frank, 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - Terboss, Margaret Cook, 1943-1946; 1948-1953,; undated; secretary (Box 4)
    - Watson, Thomas J., 1943; 1951-1952 (Box 4)
    - Young, Joseph S., 1938-1943; 1945-1948,; 1951,; undated (Box 4)
    - Young, Marion, 1938; 1941,; undated; daughter (Box 4)
    - Young, William, 1941; 1942,; 1946,; 1951,; 1953,; undated; grandson (Box 4)
    - Workers, unidentified, 1940; undated (Box 4)
    - Not identified, 1934; 1945,; 1951,; 1952,; undated (Box 4)
  - Outgoing
    - 1924, 1931, 1932-1936 (Box 4)
    - 1937-1939 (Box 4)
    - 1940, 1941 (Box 5)
    - 1942, 1943 (Box 5)
    - 1944, 1945 (Box 5)
    - 1946, 1947 (Box 5)
    - 1948, 1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950 (Box 5)
    - 1951
      - Jan. - Feb. (Box 5)
      - March, April (Box 5)
      - May, June (Box 5)
      - July, August (Box 5)
      - Sept. - Oct. (Box 6)
      - Nov., Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1952
      - Jan., Feb. (Box 6)
      - March, April (Box 6)
      - May, June (Box 6)
      - July, Aug. (Box 6)
      - Sept., Oct. (Box 6)
      - Nov., Dec. (Box 6)
    - 1953 (Box 6)
    - undated (Box 6)
  - Correspondence of others
    - Johnson, Frank, 1938; 1952; son (Box 6)
    - Johnson, George F., 1946 (Box 6)
    - Johnson, Lula, 1937; 1938,; 1950,; 1952,; 1953,; undated; wife (Box 6)
    - Sweet, Lillian, 1942; 1949; sister (Box 6)
    - Terboss, Margaret Cook, 1937; 1939,; 1940,; 1944,; 1947,; 1951-1954,; 1962; secretary (Box 6)
- Subject files
  - Bata Shoe Co., undated (Box 7)
  - Bills and receipts, 1921; 1922,; 1931,; 1947-1953 (Box 7)
  - Blueprints, 1923; 1942,; 1945-1947,; 1951,; 1952 (Box 7)
  - Citation, Greater Endicott Chamber of Commerce, 1946 (Box 7)
  - Company airplane, 1951; 1952 (Box 7)
  - Drawing of George W. Johnson, undated (Box 7)
  - Endicott-Johnson Athletic Association, 1951-1953 (Box 7)
  - Endicott-Johnson Workers' Band, 1952 (Box 7)
  - Family history, 1944 (Box 8)
  - Grumman airplane, 1946 (Box 8)
  - Charles F. Johnson, Jr., 1936; 1953,; undated (Box 8)
  - George F. Johnson, 1938; 1951 (Box 8)
  - Harry L. Johnson, undated (Box 8)
  - Labor Day, 1951; 1952 (Box 8)
  - Legal department, 1946 (Box 8)
  - Lists, 1938; 1951-1952 (Box 8)
  - Legal documents, 1938; 1942,; 1953,; undated (Box 8)
  - Medical department, 1944; 1948,; 1949 (Box 8)
  - Meetings, 1941; 1943,; 1951-1953 (Box 8)
  - Merit Shoe Co., 1935; 1939 (Box 8)
  - National Labor Relations Board, 1939; 1942 (Box 8)
  - Notes, 1942; 1943,; 1945,; 1946,; 1949,; 1951-1953 (Box 8)
  - Petawagama Lake, 1941; 1945,; 1950,; 1951,; undated (Box 8)
  - Pensions and death benefits, 1944; 1946,; 1947 (Box 9)
  - Press copy, 1941-1946 (Box 9)
  - Programs, 1937; 1951,; 1953,; undated (Box 9)
  - Reports
    - 1934, 1936, 1938 (Box 9)
    - 1940, 1942, 1943, 1945-1947, 1950-1951 (Box 9)
    - 1952-1953 (Box 9)
  - Safety department (Box 9)
  - Signature of George W. Johnson (Box 9)
  - Sole leather setting department, undated (Box 9)
  - Tannery department, 1943; 1951 (Box 9)
  - Tape G.W.J. funeral, 5/28/53 (Box 9)
  - Unions
    - 1938, 1939 (Box 10)
    - 1940, NLRB Election (correspondence) (Box 10)
    - 1941-1943 (Box 10)
    - 1944 (Box 10)
    - 1945 (Box 10)
    - 1946, 1949, 1950, 1952, undated (Box 10)
  - Wages, 1939-1944 (Box 10)
  - Workers' homes, 1923; 1926 (Box 10)
- Manuscripts
  - By, 1936; 1944,; 1949 (Box 11)
  - By George F. Johnson, 1925; 1935 (Box 11)
  - Of others, 1939; undated (Box 11)
- Mimeographed and printed notices
  - 1921, 1931-1939 (Box 12)
  - 1940, 1941 (Box 12)
  - 1942 (Box 12)
  - 1943 (Box 12)
  - 1944 (Box 12)
  - 1945 (Box 12)
  - 1946 (Box 12)
  - 1947 (Box 12)
  - 1948 (Box 12)
  - 1949 (Box 12)
  - 1950 (Box 12)
  - 1951 (Box 12)
  - 1952 (Box 12)
  - 1953 (Box 12)
  - undated (Box 12)
- Photographs
  - Airplane, 1945 (Box 13)
  - Ralph B. Clark, 1952 (Box 13)
  - Endicott-Johnson officers, 1941 (Box 13)
  - Endicott-Johnson plant, 1936 (Box 13)
  - Charles F. Johnson, Jr., 1947 (Box 13)
  - George F. Johnson, undated (Box 13)
  - Negative, undated (Box 13)
  - Self, 1890; 1944,; 1949 (Box 13)
  - Workers and miscellaneous, 1943; undated (Box 13)
  - Young Building, undated (Oversize 1)
- Workers' pages
  - 1931, 6 folders (Box 14)
  - 1932, 6 folders (Box 14)
  - 1933, 7 folders (Box 15)
  - 1934, January-October, 6 folders (Box 15)
  - 1934, November-December (Box 16)
  - 1935, 8 folders (Box 16)
  - 1936, January-March, 3 folders (Box 16)
  - 1936, April-December, 9 folders (Box 17)
  - 1937, January-September, 5 folders (Box 17)
  - 1937, October-December, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1938, 8 folders (Box 18)
  - 1939, January-March, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - 1939, April-December, 8 folders (Box 19)
  - 1940, 7 folders (Box 19)
  - 1941, 11 folders (Box 20)
  - 1942, January-June, 3 folders (Box 20)
  - 1942, July-December, 4 folders (Box 21)
  - 1943, 7 folders (Box 21)
  - 1944, 11 folders (Box 22)
  - 1945, January-August, 4 folders (Box 22)
  - 1945, September-December, 2 folders (Box 23)
  - 1946, 11 folders (Box 23)
  - 1947, 12 folders (Box 24)
- Published material
  - Articles by
    - George W. Johnson, 1936 (Box 25)
    - George F. Johnson, 1922; 1931,; 1934,; 1937,; undated (Box 25)
    - Billy Young, 1926; grandson (Box 25)
  - Articles by and about others, 1921; 1922,; 1937,; 1944,; 1945,; 1948,; 1950-1952,; undated (Box 25)
  - Brochures
    - Endicott-Johnson, 1944; 1946,; 1947,; 1949,; undated (Box 25)
    - Others
      - 1936, 1938, 1941, 1943-1947 (Box 25)
      - 1950-1952 (Box 25)
      - undated (Box 25)
  - Bulletin board notices
    - 1939-1941, 1943 (Box 26)
    - 1944 (Box 26)
    - 1945, 1946 (Box 26)
    - 1947, 1948 (Box 26)
    - 1949, 1950 (Box 27)
  - Magazines, E-J Workers Review
    - 1921 March (Box 27)
    - 1922 Nov.- Dec., 2 copies of November (Box 27)
    - 1923 March, April, May, June, Aug. (Box 27)
    - 1924 June (Box 27)
    - 1925 Feb., March, April, May, Aug., Oct. (Box 27)
  - Newsletters
    - The Morning Sun, published by E.J. Workers' Club, Communist Party, 1951; 1952 (Box 27)
    - Various, 1950-1953 (Box 27)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About George W
      - 1936-1953 (Box 27)
      - 1956 (Box 28)
    - By, 1940-1949 (Box 28)
    - About others
      - Charles F. Johnson, Jr., 1934; 1950,; 1952,; undated (Box 28)
      - Endicott-Johnson Corp.
        - 1938-1952, 3 folders (Box 28)
        - 1952-1953, undated (Box 29)
      - George F. Johnson, 1940-1948; 1950-1956; 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Johnson family, 1947; 1950-1952,; 1956,; undated (Box 29)
  - By and about others, 1943-1956; 2 folders (Box 29)
  - "Listen World" by Elsie Robinson, 1945; 1946,; 1948-1950 (Box 29)